<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-13T11:46:23+12:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">mlog</title><subtitle>Sharing what is happening with machine learning at Jade, with mostly pictures and words, one algorithm at a time.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Algorithm, the beat</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/12/algorithm-a-star-is-born.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Algorithm, the beat" /><published>2019-02-12T09:28:00+13:00</published><updated>2019-02-12T09:28:00+13:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/12/algorithm-a-star-is-born</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/12/algorithm-a-star-is-born.html">&lt;p&gt;INT. ALLY’S HOUSE - CLOSE ON CELL PHONE - EARLY MORNING&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE’RE LOOKING AT A YOUTUBE VIDEO OF THEIR DUET.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOLFIE: What’s that number down here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MATTY: That is how many people looked at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we see Lorenzo’s racetrack and driver compadres are
clustered together in Ally’s living room, as one of them
is holding a cell phone for the others to see…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOLFIE: Get the fuck outta here. How do they know how many people looked at it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LITTLE FEET: They call it an algorithm…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOLFIE: What’s an algorithm?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MATTY: It’s like a beat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOLFIE: A beat?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MATTY: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOLFIE: Like in music, a beat?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MATTY: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorenzo comes in and sees what they’re looking at…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LORENZO: Do you believe this? And you see this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He points to the growing number on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOLFIE: Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LORENZO: That’s how many people have watched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOLFIE: Yeah, yeah, we…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MATTY: We were telling him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WOLFIE: How the fuck do they do that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LORENZO: I watched it two hundred times myself. I’m two hundred of those people.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">INT. ALLY’S HOUSE - CLOSE ON CELL PHONE - EARLY MORNING</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Not just numbers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/11/recommender-for-construction-planning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Not just numbers" /><published>2019-02-11T14:11:00+13:00</published><updated>2019-02-11T14:11:00+13:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/11/recommender-for-construction-planning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/11/recommender-for-construction-planning.html">&lt;p&gt;Working with Harrison Grierson, a construction planning company based in Tauranga, we provided a document-recommender machine learning service. Using text analytics, the machine learning model “reads” and analyses documents from thousands of past projects to recommend those that are most related to the document currently being viewed. The filtered list of recommendations enables knowledge sharing across the country in addition to saving engineers and planners significant time searching and browsing through projects and folders manually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the proof of concept, we extracted texts from more than 2500 Microsoft Word documents and PDFs within 30 sample projects. For each of the documents, we compiled a list of keywords by counting occurence of a word in the document and normalising the occurrence to a wider collection of documents (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tf%E2%80%93idf&quot;&gt;TF-IDF&lt;/a&gt; is the technical term). We fed the keywords into &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FastText&quot;&gt;Facebook’s text library&lt;/a&gt; to compare the meaning of the keywords in 300 dimensions. Each dimension has its own explanation e.g. gender, royalty, sports etc or combinations of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the common English words which are not included as keywords by default, we worked with the engineers and planners on the words that are common in the industry that should be ignored (such as company names). 
We have also built a &lt;a href=&quot;https://jadeai.shinyapps.io/recommenderdemo&quot;&gt;user interface&lt;/a&gt; (email me for access) that recommends keyword, document and project that are most related. When the planners and engineers from Harrison Grierson look up say 3 primary keywords, the machine learning model recommends what other keywords they may be interested in. The plot below shows the 3 primary keywords (big blue dots) and how they are interconnected in this two-degree network. Each of the 3 keywords has 2 layers of 6 most-related keywords. The two layers are coloured orange or green respectively. Hovering over the dots in user interface will tell the users which word each of the dots represents. 
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/keyword_network.png&quot; alt=&quot;keyword network&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;surfacing-similar-documents-and-similar-projects&quot;&gt;Surfacing similar documents and similar projects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on keywords and keywords with similar meaning, we surfaced similar documents. Similar documents mean a pair of documents with matching keywords or keywords with similar meaning within the 300 dimensions. Subsequently, similar projects are simply projects with high number of similar documents.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Working with Harrison Grierson, a construction planning company based in Tauranga, we provided a document-recommender machine learning service. Using text analytics, the machine learning model “reads” and analyses documents from thousands of past projects to recommend those that are most related to the document currently being viewed. The filtered list of recommendations enables knowledge sharing across the country in addition to saving engineers and planners significant time searching and browsing through projects and folders manually.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where is the train? Choo choo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/08/predicting-train-delays.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where is the train? Choo choo" /><published>2019-02-08T09:08:00+13:00</published><updated>2019-02-08T09:08:00+13:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/02/08/predicting-train-delays</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/02/08/predicting-train-delays.html">&lt;p&gt;In Q4 2018, we ran a 4-week project to extract 2 years’ worth of train trip data to to develop a machine learning model that predicts ETA of a train. We have used data from 2016 and 2017 to train our machine learning models. To emulate how the models would be implemented, we applied the models to predict events in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the proof of concept, we used data from 4 DB Cargo’s customers, namely British Steel, Mendip Rail, Tarmac and Puma Energy. We cleansed and aggregated 30,000 train trips from the ECOS system using our bespoke pre-processing methods. We calculated measures about the trips such as delays in the first two stations, busyness of the next stations and distance to final destinations. Overall, we processed 40 of these measures for every trip, which equate to a total of more than 1.2 million data points. Day of week is one of the 40 measures included in the machine learning model. The plot below shows delays distributed across Monday to Sunday. In this case Sunday clearly has the least proportion of early/late arrivals.
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/delays_vs_days_of_week.png&quot; alt=&quot;delay vs. days of week&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All trips were also tagged with the early arrival or delay in minutes. The goal of machine learning algorithms is to find the correlations of the 40 measures with the delay or early arrival. To achieve this, the processed data was fed into multiple machine learning algorithms and the one with the best performance was selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the machine learning model is to guide human decision-making in taking follow-up actions. An example of follow-up actions for this model may include; deploying workers later or earlier based on predicted arrival time, but also more effective use of physical rail resource, planning and scheduling. 
We have provided a demonstration of the performance of the model for DB Cargo on an interactive &lt;a href=&quot;https://jadeai.shinyapps.io/traindelays/&quot;&gt;visualisation platform&lt;/a&gt; (email me for access).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aspects of the research project have immediately led to investigations to integrate train ETA into the DB Cargo Customer Portal based on the ML model. This includes expanding the machine learning model to incorporate all of DB Cargo’s current customers. Incorporating additional data. For example, weather data and passenger-train data is also expected to lift the performance to give more accurate predictions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In Q4 2018, we ran a 4-week project to extract 2 years’ worth of train trip data to to develop a machine learning model that predicts ETA of a train. We have used data from 2016 and 2017 to train our machine learning models. To emulate how the models would be implemented, we applied the models to predict events in 2018.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jade’s ML on the news!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/29/jade-ml-on-the-news.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jade's ML on the news!" /><published>2019-01-29T12:14:00+13:00</published><updated>2019-01-29T12:14:00+13:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/29/jade-ml-on-the-news</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/01/29/jade-ml-on-the-news.html">&lt;p&gt;We were on the news twice last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stuff.co.nz/national/education/103721516/this-machine-learning-algorithm-claims-to-know-which-students-are-going-to-drop-out&quot;&gt;Machine learning algorithm is claimed to predict which students will drop out&lt;/a&gt; showcases our first ever predictive model (built by our summer interns) to predict which students are the most likely going to drop out of a university. We have been working on a piece of research work to roll out this NZ-wide!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stuff.co.nz/technology/108106300/algorithms-are-everywhere-but-the-public-sector-seems-scared-to-use-them&quot;&gt;Algorithms are everywhere but the public sector seems scared to use them&lt;/a&gt; interviews me as a public servant turned corporate citizen. It was my first time being interviewed on national paper and I was worried about how the reporter would quote me out of context. It turned out she was pretty much pinpoint accurate so the article very much reflects what I see as the positive outlook of using algorithms in the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We were on the news twice last year.</summary></entry></feed>